# **Christopher Tastad** | Letter

720 Washington Ave S #507 - Minneapolis, MN 55415 - USA

HR Department
\*\*\*
STREET ADDRESS
CITY, STATE ZIP

December 9, 2019

To Whom It May Concern,

I am interested in applying for the \*\*\* position with \*\*\*. With my background, I provide a unique blend of content knowledge, technical analysis, and relevant experience that make me a strong fit for the role. I have brought this aptitude together through a few core principles which I have applied in a diverse range of settings. Critical thinking and objectivity guide my approach; independence and competency carry to completion; and an attraction towards establishing effective systems elevates outcomes.

My first and most prominent experience was in stem cell development with a disease model of muscular dystrophy. As a research associate in The Stem Cell Institute, I worked in a central role through independent project coordination, grant and manuscript writing, lab member training, and overall lab management. While serving in this position, I employed strict research methodology and analysis to produce publication quality data. With that, I often presented and defended my efforts to both my primary investigator and the broader scientific community. The product of this work led to several co-authorships in high impact journals as well as being awarded individual grant monies with contributions to lab-wide grants.

Additionally, in recent history, I have focused in the study of handling large data sets, particularly in Bioinformatics. As an integrative field, I've brought my medical content knowledge forward with the development of advanced skill sets in statistical and computational modeling. By developing expertise in this area, I have drastically expanded the nature, flexibility, and application of the analytics capabilities that underline my scientific training. Most importantly, my ability to work with large data sets has become subject agnostic and can translate to any intensive technical task, all of which would be well suited to \*\*\*'s business objectives.

Taken together, I would appreciate further consideration and an opportunity to interview with \*\*\* for the \*\*\* role. Please feel free to contact me at (612) 817–7989 or ctastad@gmail.com.

Sincerely Yours,

#### **Christopher Tastad**

Attached: Resume

# **Christopher Tastad** | Resume

720 Washington Ave S #507 - Minneapolis, MN 55415 - USA

612) 817–7989 • ☐ ctastad@gmail.com • ☐ ctastad • in ctastad

## **Education**

Bioinformatics. MS

Minneapolis, MN

University of Minnesota, Bioinformatics and Computational Biology

Sept 2015 — Present

Biochemistry, BS

Minneapolis, MN

University of Minnesota, College of Biological Sciences

Sept 2007 — May 2011

## Skills

Languages: R, BASH, LATEX, SQL, HTML, CSS, XML

Platforms: Linux, GIT, NGINX, APACHE, Relational Databases, Oracle, Vim, wordpress, virtual machines, proxmox,

docker containerization, HPC, vector graphics, visualization

Packages: rmarkdown, shiny, ggplot2, dplyr, tidyr, BioC, SummarizedExperiment, DNAcopy, GRL PACKAGES

Genomics: samtools, bwa-mem, CNV (VarScan2, Excavator), Single Cell (Seurat)

Statistics: Hypothesis testing, Simple/Multiple/Poisson Regression, A/B Testing, Contingency Testing, ANOVA, Survival Analysis, K-means, PCA, K-nearest neighbor, SVM, Bayesian Networks, Functional Linkage Networks

Benchwork: DNA/RNA/protein isolation and analysis, western blotting, PCR, ELISA, luciferase, immunostaining, histology, epigenetic analysis, FACS, mammalian cell culture

## **Experience**

### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Minneapolis, MN

Department of OBGYN, Starr Lab

May 2019 — Present

o test

**Load Planner** United Parcel Service, Industrial Engineering Minneapolis, MN

Oct 2018 — Present

o Central point person in coordinating all hub-wide load related functions; mediating hub, feeder, and engineering priorities.

- o Advance district level interests through industrial engineering functions of operational, flow, and system analysis.
- o Operate with a wide latitude in exploring opportunities for cost saving measures for management and stakeholders.

Supervisor

Minneapolis, MN Oct 2017 — Oct 2018

United Parcel Service, Small Sort

- o Managed a team of 35 employees in largest operational unit in the Northern Plains District HQ sort hub.
- o Brought an immediate 15% production increase to area within first month with sustained production improvements.
- o Developed and led significant improvement projects around personnel training, volume recovery, and missort reduction.

Package Sorter United Parcel Service Minneapolis, MN

June 2017 — Oct 2017

## **Graduate Research Assistant**

Minneapolis, MN

National Marrow Donor Program, Bioinformatics

Jan 2016 — July 2017

- o Employed scientific method as an investigator in a big data R&D department with a focus in hematological cancer treatment.
- o Took both basic and clinical approach to investigation in cell therapy, immunology, and organ transplant genetics.
- o Conducted analysis through R with Rstudio, Rmarkdown, and Rshiny, Python, and NextGen Sequencing data pipelines.

### **Biorepository Technician**

New Brighton, MN

National Marrow Donor Program, Research Repository

Sept 2014 — Jan 2016

- o Was responsible for research specimen processing in high-throughput clinical laboratory facility.
- Managed database and long-term storage for FDA and Bone Marrow Transplant Clinical Trials Network samples using GLP.
- o Contributed to larger registry activities maintaining Be The Match patient/donor sample receiving, storage and typing.

### **Banquet and Dining Server**

Minneapolis, MN

Minneapolis Club

Oct 2013 — Sept 2014

- o Worked setup, service, and take down for dining room and banquets ranging from chef's table dinners to events of 500+.
- o Trained in the manner of French service and hospitality to maintain an elite level of accommodation and experience.
- Contributed to maintenance and building upkeep when necessary.

Co-founder St. Anthony, MN

Face to Face Organics LLC.

July 2012 — Jan 2014

- o Co-founded a personal care products start up that connected social activism with our product and its use.
- o Deployed company's operating software stack on limited budget with minimal upfront cost and sustained overhead.
- o Contributed software proficiency in e-commerce, CRM, distribution, logistics, accounting, sales tracking, and inventory.

Research Associate Minneapolis, MN

The Stem Cell Institute, Asakura Lab

Dec 2007 — Jan 2013

- Conducted basic science research with a focus in skeletal muscle development, receiving 4 co-authorships.
- o Well versed in full spectrum of molecular biology, histology and cell biology wet lab techniques and diagnostics.
- o Contributed significant writing efforts toward group manuscripts and major grant awards, including a sucessful R01 bid.

Teaching Assistant St. Paul, MN

University of Minnesota, CBS Biol2004

Sept 2009 — May 2012

- Led teaching lab that included an integrative, research-focused curriculum, highlighting significant independent discovery.
- o Was consistently called on by course instructor for consultation in the improvement of course materials and curriculum.
- o Received highest rating among all course TAs as indicated by students in post-semester evaluations for 2012 year.

#### Founder, Lobbyist, and Chairman

Minneapolis, MN

Minnesota Student Legislative Coalition

Oct 2009 — July 2012

- o United leaders from all 5 U of MN campuses to form the active student lobby, earning the University's endorsement.
- o Directed issues involving education funding, loan rates, textbook pricing, campus safety, and veteran accreditation.
- o Trained and supervised a team that guided the authorship of 4 student-specific bills during 2012 state legislative session.

## **Personal**

Volunteering...

Hobbies: Racquetball, CAD design & 3d printing, Camping, Fishing, Hunting, Reading, Self-hosting software

IT Consultant

Montevideo, MN
July 2017 — Present

Trinity Lutheran Church of Montevideo

Youth Camp Racquetball Coach

Minneapolis, MN
July 2017 — July 2017

University of Minnesota, Recwell

, 2017 Suly 2017

Child Life Specialist

Minneapolis, MN

Shriners Hospital for Children

Dec 2008 — May 2013

IT Consultant & Umn Chapter Co-founder

Edina, MN Nov 2008 — July 2011

Ducks Unlimited

Cape Town, South Africa

**Trauma Ward Aide**Student Travel and Exposure South Africa

June 2009 — July 2009

## **Publications**

- [1] **Tastad, C. T.** and M. Verma. RefSearch: A tool to more accurately identify normalization candidates for RNAseq analysis. *Manuscript in preparation*, 2019.
- [2] Y. Nakamura, Y. Asakura, B. A. Piras, H. Hirai, **Tastad, C. T.**, M. Verma, A. J. Christ, J. Zhang, T. Yamazaki, M. Yoshiyama, and A. Asakura. Increased angiogenesis and improved left ventricular function after transplantation of myoblasts lacking the MyoD gene into infarcted myocardium. *PLoS ONE*, 7(7):e41736, 2012.
- [3] S. Watanabe, H. Hirai, Y. Asakura, **Tastad, C**., M. Verma, C. Keller, J. R. Dutton, and A. Asakura. MyoD gene suppression by Oct4 is required for reprogramming in myoblasts to produce induced pluripotent stem cells. *Stem Cells*, 29(3):505–516, Mar 2011.
- [4] H. Hirai, M. Verma, S. Watanabe, **Tastad, C.**, Y. Asakura, and A. Asakura. MyoD regulates apoptosis of myoblasts through microRNA-mediated down-regulation of Pax3. *J. Cell Biol.*, 191(2):347–365, Oct 2010.

[5] M. Verma, Y. Asakura, H. Hirai, S. Watanabe, **Tastad, C**., G. H. Fong, M. Ema, J. A. Call, D. A. Lowe, and A. Asakura. Flt-1 haploinsufficiency ameliorates muscular dystrophy phenotype by developmentally increased vasculature in mdx mice. *Hum. Mol. Genet.*, 19(21):4145–4159, Nov 2010.

## **Awards**

Advocate of the Year: University of Minnesota Alumni Association	Oct, 2012
Spirit of MSA (MVP): Minnesota Student Association	May, 2012
Highest Rated TA: CBS Biol2004 Lab Students	May, 2012
Research Fellowship: Gregory Marzolf Jr. Foundation	Sept, 2009
Distinct Honor — Presenter's Award: LHI/SCI Building Muscle and Blood Conference	Oct, 2009
Undergraduate Research Opportunity Grant: University of Minnesota	2008, 2009, 2011